British Columbia and Yukon Association of Women's Centres fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
British Columbia and Yukon Association of Women's Centres fonds
1986 - 1999
F-123
Q104892397
94 cm of textual records 6 photographs
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
The six photographs are included in series 5, "Correspondence", file 11 ("Correspondence, 1994").
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by the Government of Canada through the National Archival Development Program, a program delivered by the Canadian Council of Archives in partnership with Library and Archives Canada (March 2009).
British Columbia and Yukon Association of Women's Centres
The British Columbia and Yukon Association of Women's Centres (BCYAWC) was founded in 1985 as an umbrella organization of over 30 women's centres. It ceased operations in 1998.
Women's centres developed in the 1970s as a project of the women's movement. They served as women-only space to practice an egalitarian model of organization. They were devoted to improving the status of women through education and political action and to helping women through the provision of safe space, support, and services. Over the years, the number of women using women's centres increased as the centres struggled to find ongoing funding.
By 1984, women's centres were looking for a more structured way to work towards common goals, including secure funding and improved cooperation and communication among centres. In 1985 they established the BCYAWC and incorporated under the BC Society Act on November 12, 1987. By 1990, the BCYAWC consisted of 31 women's resource centres – 30 in BC, one in the Yukon. The Association was managed by a volunteer coordinating collective that included a secretary, treasurer, 11 regional representatives, and six members-at-large. Meetings were scheduled for four times a year.
Around 1993 the group began to lose its cohesiveness because of funding and other issues. In 1995, the province cut the Association's funding. The following year, the Association was struck from the Registry of Societies for failure to file required documentation such as audited financial statements. While the Association made an attempt to file the papers necessary to regain status, the remaining members in 1998 agreed to dissolve the organization and distribute its assets.
published
Full
Published
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator. Titles of series were supplied by the archivist based on the contents of series. At the file level, titles are based on the creator's folder names.
Fonds consists of records made or recieved by the Association in the course of its activities. Activities documented include incorporation; meetings of the Annual General Meeting and various committees; maintenance of membership; financial management, budget planning, and grant applications; correspondence with member centres, regional representatives, government ministries and agencies, and other organizations; and development of a training strategy ("Planning for Change") and other projects. Records include correspondence, reports, meeting minutes and supporting papers, policies and procedures, financial records, agreements, published materials retained for reference, and notes, drafts and working papers.
The records were maintained by the creator as a single block of office files, and the arrangement of the fonds into series was provided by the archivist in order to facilitate intellectual access to the records. Series were established on a functional basis, grouping together records generated by similar activities. Researchers should be aware that overlap among groupings occurs, and the entire file list for the fonds should be reviewed to determine the existence of all files on a particular subject.
Within series, files are typically arranged chronologically; exceptions only will be noted in series descriptions. Within files, documents are generally organized chronologically, though strict chronological order was not always originally maintained within files nor has it been supplied by the archivist.
Photographic materials; Textual records; Women
As of April 2009, all accessions have been processed. No further accruals are expected.
Upon its dissolution, over two metres of the Association's records were in the custody of its volunteer secretary, Janet Dahr. Ms Dahr donated the materials to the SFU Archives in April 2003 and in May 2003 the Archives formally accessioned and took custody and control of the records.
The SFU Archives also holds the archival records of two women's centres that were members of the BCYAWC. See:
- F-40, Simon Fraser University Women's Centre fonds (1972-2000).
- F-76, Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre fonds (1974-1996).
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the reference archivist for more details.
File lists are available.
- Organization records, 1987 - 1995; F-123-1; 6 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the establishment, structure and governance of the Association. Activities documented include incorporation, policy development, and liaison with the provincial Ministry of Women's Equality. Records includes certificate of incorporation, constitutions, policies and procedures, and correspondence.
  - Incorporation, 1987 - 1994; F-123-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Women's centres in BC, 1990; F-123-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Letterhead and forms, [ca 1990]; F-123-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Policies, 1992 - 1995; F-123-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - BCYAWC and Ministry of Women's Equality joint planning session, 1994; F-123-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Orientation Manual, 1994 - 1995; F-123-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Ministry of Women's Equality, 1995; F-123-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - New members package, 1995; F-123-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
- Minutes, 1987 - 1998; F-123-2; 19 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to various meetings associated with the organization. Activities documented include Annual General Meetings; the meetings of several committees, including the Steering Committee, Negotiating Committee, and Coordinating Collective; and meetings of women's centres from across BC / Yukon. Records include minutes, agendas, correspondence, reports, notes and working papers.
  Files are generally arranged chronologically, with the exception that all of the Annual General Meeting files (1987-1998) are grouped together at the head of the file list.
  Other records relating to the activities of Assocation committees can be found throughout the correspondence files in series 5, "Correspondence".
  - Annual General Meetings, 1987 - 1990; F-123-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Annual General Meeting, 1990; F-123-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Annual General Meeting, 1991; F-123-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Annual General Meeting, 1992; F-123-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Annual General Meeting, vol. 1, 1993; F-123-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Annual General Meeting, vol. 2, 1993; F-123-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Annual General Meeting, 1994; F-123-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Annual General Meeting, 1995; F-123-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 123-1)
  - Annual General Meeting, 1997 - 1998; F-123-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 123-2)
  - Steering Committee minutes and notes, 1989 - 1990; F-123-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 123-2)
  - Minutes - general, 1990; F-123-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 123-2)
  - Negotiating Committee minutes, 1992 - 1993; F-123-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 123-2)
  - Coordinating Collective minutes, 1994 - 1995; F-123-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 123-2)
  - Coordinating Collective minutes, 1995 - 1996; F-123-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 123-2)
  - Women's centres meetings, 1996; F-123-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 123-2)
  - Meetings - general, 1997 - 1998; F-123-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 123-2)
- Membership records, 1990 - 1999; F-123-3; 6 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the participation of member organizations in the BC and Yukon Association of Women's Centres. Records include membership forms, directories and lists, correspondence, and certificates of membership.
  - Membership, 1990; F-123-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Membership, 1991 - 1992; F-123-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Membership, 1992; F-123-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Membership, 1993 - 1994; F-123-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Membership, 1994 - 1995; F-123-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Blank membership certificate, 1994 - 1996; F-123-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Membership, 1995 - 1996; F-123-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Membership dues, 1997 - 1999; F-123-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
- Financial records, 1988 - 1999; F-123-4; 19 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the Association's management of its financial resources. Activities documented include applying for grants, budgeting, preparing financial statements and tax returns, reporting to funding agencies, and financial auditing. Records include grant applications, income tax returns, financial statements, ledgers, correspondence, reports, agreements, and contracts.
  Further material relating to finances can be found in the correspondence files in series 5, "Correspondence." Project financial records are often included in the files in series 6, "Project records."
  - Funding application - Secretary of State, 1988 - 1989; F-123-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Corporate income tax forms (T2), 1988 - 1992; F-123-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Financial statements, 1989 - 1990; F-123-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Grant application, 1989 - 1990; F-123-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Budget, 1990; F-123-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Secretary of State evaluation, 1990 - 1991; F-123-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Grants, 1990 - 1994; F-123-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Ledgers, 1990 - 1994; F-123-4-0-0-8
  - Financial statements, 1991 - 1992; F-123-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 123-3)
  - Financial statements, 1992; F-123-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Funding - Secretary of State, 1992; F-123-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Operational funding, 1992 - 1995; F-123-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Financial statements, 1993; F-123-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Operational funding, 1993 - 1994; F-123-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Contract, applications and reports, 1994 - 1995; F-123-4-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Ministry of Women's Equality grant application, 1994 - 1995; F-123-4-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Financial audit, 1994 - 1996; F-123-4-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Financial statements, 1994 - 1996; F-123-4-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Operational funding agreement, 1995; F-123-4-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Treasurer's binder - correspondence, vol. 1, 1997 - 1999; F-123-4-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Treasurer's binder - correspondence, vol. 2, 1997 - 1999; F-123-4-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
  - Corporate tax returns, 1998 - 1999; F-123-4-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 123-4)
- Correspondence, 1986 - 1997; F-123-5; 25 cm of textual records 6 photographs; The six photographs are included in file F-123-5-0-0-11 ("Correspondence, 1994").
  Series consists of records relating to the day-to-day operations of the BC and Yukon Association of Women's Centres. Activities documented include meetings of the Steering Committee and Coordinating Collective, financial accounting, grants management, project planning, policy development, liaison with the BC and federal governments, political activism, and reporting news from individual women's centres.
  Because of the informal record-keeping of the Association, the files contain other document types besides letters sent and received. Records also include minutes, agendas, invoices, vouchers, bills, financial statements, forms, news releases, newsletters, reports, briefs, position papers, project proposals, drafts, working papers and notes.
  - Correspondence, 1986 - 1989; F-123-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 123-5)
  - Correspondence, 1990; F-123-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 123-5)
  - Correspondence, vol. 1, 1990 - 1991; F-123-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 123-5)
  - Correspondence, vol. 2, 1990 - 1991; F-123-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 123-5)
  - Correspondence, vol. 1, 1992; F-123-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 123-5)
  - Correspondence, vol. 2, 1992; F-123-5-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 123-5)
  - Correspondence, vol. 1, 1993; F-123-5-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 123-5)
  - Correspondence, vol. 2, 1993; F-123-5-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 123-6)
  - Correspondence, vol. 1, 1993 - 1995; F-123-5-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 123-6)
  - Correspondence, vol. 2, 1993 - 1995; F-123-5-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 123-6)
  - Correspondence, 1994; F-123-5-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 123-6)
    Textual records; Photographic materials
  - Correspondence, 1995; F-123-5-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 123-6)
  - Correspondence, 1996; F-123-5-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 123-6)
  - Correspondence, 1997; F-123-5-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 123-6)
- Project records, 1989 - 1995; F-123-6; 19 cm of textual records; British Columbia and Yukon Association of Women's Centres. Committee for the Planning for Change Project
  In 1991 the British Columbia and Yukon Association of Women's Centres (BCYAWC) initiated a training strategy called Planning for Change. It was preceded by a needs assessment questionnaire sent to member centres to identify the organizational and resource problems to be addressed by such a strategy and uncover solutions to common problems. The results were used to develop training workshops and a resource manual, "From Burnout to Breakthrough." The manual was completed in 1993. It begins with an historical overview of the development of women's centres and includes guidelines for operating a centre including fundraising, marketing, recruitment, and outreach.
  Series consists primarily of records relating to the Planning for Change training strategy, but also contains files relating to a few other smaller projects undertaken by the Association. Records include correspondence, proposals, contracts, letters of agreement, meeting agendas and minutes, briefs, reports, reprints, financial statements, drafts, notes, and working papers.
  British Columbia and Yukon Association of Women's Centres. Committee for the Planning for Change Project
  - Wife assault project, 1989; F-123-6-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Computer network, 1989 - 1990; F-123-6-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Needs assessment questionnaire - responses, vol. 1, 1991; F-123-6-0-0-3 (Archival box - small 123-7)
  - Needs assessment questionnaire - responses, vol. 2, 1991; F-123-6-0-0-4 (Archival box - small 123-7)
  - Needs assessment questionnaire - report, 1991; F-123-6-0-0-5 (Archival box - small 123-7)
  - Planning for Change - correspondence, budget, 1990 - 1992; F-123-6-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Training strategy, 1990 - 1993; F-123-6-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Train the Trainers Workshop, 1991; F-123-6-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Training strategy, 1991 - 1993; F-123-6-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Building Links: A Women's Conference, 1992; F-123-6-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Training strategy, 1992 - 1993; F-123-6-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Training strategy, 1992 - 1994; F-123-6-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Resource Manual: Burnout to Breakthrough, 1993; F-123-6-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Training strategy, 1993; F-123-6-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 123-8)
  - Training report, 1993 - 1995; F-123-6-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 123-8)